<p xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par9">Given the crucial role of accurate tumor grading in prognosis and treatment planning, particularly for distinguishing G1 from G2 NETs that have distinct clinical outcomes, it is essential to rely on robust markers for grading. Proliferation itself can be measured by the mitosis count or Ki67 score, where the latter proved to be a better indicator of biological behavior<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. The reliability of the Ki67 score increases with the size of the evaluated area, as a larger area provides a greater number of positively and negatively stained cells, resulting in a more statistically accurate reflection of the proliferation rate in the whole slide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. However, manual cell counting is a time-consuming task, and its application in a large area is impractical in routine diagnostics. As a compromise between time efficiency and reliability of the estimated Ki67 score, counting a minimum of 500-2,000 tumor cells is recommended<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Basing the measurement on a large number of cells is especially crucial for low proliferative tumors, in which counting only a limited number of tumor cells can easily lead to incorrect results<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Despite this, due to increased workload<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> pathologists often opt for eyeballing, which in turn suffers from lack of reproducibility, precision, and accuracy and is further affected by inter-observer variability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Furthermore, a correct estimation of the Ki67 score relies on familiarity with histopathological subtleties of a given tumor. For instance, the presence of intra-tumoral lymphocytes or heavily inflamed tumor stroma may result in overestimation of the Ki67 score<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Therefore, there is a need for an unbiased, fast, and reliable analytical method for Ki67 score estimation.</p>