<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="hsr271167" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jats-oasis2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2398-8835</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HSR2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Health Science Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2398-8835</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">12344509</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hsr2.71167</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">HSR271167</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis and Mapping of Machine Learning in the Context of Diabetes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="hsr271167-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghamgosar</surname><given-names>Arezoo</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8805-0325</contrib-id><xref rid="hsr271167-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="hsr271167-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nemati&#x02010;Anaraki</surname><given-names>Leila</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9436-2533</contrib-id><xref rid="hsr271167-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="hsr271167-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zarghani</surname><given-names>Maryam</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8702-1298</contrib-id><xref rid="hsr271167-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="hsr271167-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bazri</surname><given-names>Hooman</given-names></name><xref rid="hsr271167-aff-0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="hsr271167-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmadian</surname><given-names>Leila</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6487-2209</contrib-id><xref rid="hsr271167-aff-0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="hsr271167-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Galavi</surname><given-names>Zahra</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1179-0055</contrib-id><xref rid="hsr271167-aff-0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="hsr271167-cr-0007" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Norouzi</surname><given-names>Somaye</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1695-3810</contrib-id><xref rid="hsr271167-aff-0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref><address><email>Norouzis921@gmail.com</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="hsr271167-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Medical Biotechnology Research Center, School of Paramedical</named-content>
<institution>Guilan University of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>Rasht</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><aff id="hsr271167-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Medical Library and Information Sciences, School of Health Management and Information Sciences</named-content>
<institution>Iran University of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>Tehran</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><aff id="hsr271167-aff-0003">
<label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Medical Library and Information Science, Central Library and Medical Information, Management of medical information</named-content>
<institution>Hamadan University of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>Hamadan</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><aff id="hsr271167-aff-0004">
<label>
<sup>4</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Computer, Roudsar and Amlash Branch</named-content>
<institution>Islamic Azad University</institution>
<city>Roudsar</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><aff id="hsr271167-aff-0005">
<label>
<sup>5</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Medical Informatics Research Center, Institute for Futures Studies in Health</named-content>
<institution>Kerman University of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>Kerman</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><aff id="hsr271167-aff-0006">
<label>
<sup>6</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Health Information Technology, School of Allied Medical Sciences</named-content>
<institution>Zabol University of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>Zabol</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><aff id="hsr271167-aff-0007">
<label>
<sup>7</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Assistant Professor of Medical Informatics. Non&#x02010;Communicable Diseases Research Center, Sabzevar University of Medical Sciences, Sabzevar, Iran.</named-content>
<institution>Sabzevar University of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>Sabzevar</city>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence:</bold> Somaye Norouzi (<email>Norouzis921@gmail.com</email>)<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue seq="20">8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hsr2.v8.8</issue-id><elocation-id>e71167</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). Health Science Reports published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">Health Science Reports</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:HSR2-8-e71167.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0010"><title>Background and Aims</title><p>The application of machine learning (ML) has started to change some important aspects of health care in diabetes. We aimed to utilize a bibliometric approach to analyze and map ML in the context of diabetes.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0020"><title>Methods</title><p>To build our data set, we searched from the Web of Science Core Collection (WoSCC) database, and restricted our search from January 1, 2010 to December 31, 2023. For citation analysis, the online services of WoS were used to investigate the information content of the data set, VOSviewer and Microsoft Excel 2013 were employed to construct and visualize the bibliographic data.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0030"><title>Results</title><p>Overall, 5,222 results that met the criteria were retrieved. The trend of published studies indicates that the number of publications has steadily increased over the past 14 years. The most active country was found to be USA, followed by the China and India. The highest level of cooperation with other countries belonged to the USA. The most prolific author on ML in the context of diabetes was Tien Yin Wong, with twenty&#x02010;two articles affiliated at Tsinghua University; after that, Pantelis Georgiou with twenty articles affiliated at the Imperial College London, and Pau Herrero, with nineteen articles affiliated at Tijuana Institute of Technology. The most prolific research areas were machine learning, prediction models, diabetic retinopathy, deep learning, and diagnostics.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0040"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The results of this study are a rich scientific source of ML for diabetes to guide researchers. This study can guide policymakers, physicians, and practitioners to help in the decision&#x02010;making process. In addition, the findings will be useful for governments to guide future budgets for target studies.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="hsr271167-kwd-0001">artificial intelligence</kwd><kwd id="hsr271167-kwd-0002">bibliometric analysis</kwd><kwd id="hsr271167-kwd-0003">diabetes</kwd><kwd id="hsr271167-kwd-0004">machine learning</kwd><kwd id="hsr271167-kwd-0005">prediction model</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="5307"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>August 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.6.0 mode:remove_FC converted:13.08.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0050"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Artificial intelligence (AI) is a broad field encompassing the development of computer systems capable of performing tasks that typically require human intelligence. Machine learning (ML) is a subset of artificial intelligence (AI), and deep learning (DL) is a subfield of ML algorithms and techniques, which immediately entered the field of clinical research [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. With ML, computers can be trained to learn from data rather than being explicitly programmed, allowing them to improve their performance over time through experience. ML is a computational procedure through which a system is capable of identifying and understanding the input data and, consequently, using the obtained information in decision&#x02010;making and prediction of different events [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The application of these methods has led to extraordinary results in medical data processing, and they have been remarkably successful in diagnosing various diseases [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. A major application of ML concerning health is the diagnosis or prognosis of different diseases. Diagnostic or prognostic models can be utilized as a system to support clinical decisions to help clinicians [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In addition, they may be used as a model to predict mortality in various diseases [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>As a chronic disease, diabetes has a complex and multifactorial nature involving genetic, environmental, and behavioral interactions. ML literature can be utilized to investigate large repositories of health&#x02010;related data for this disease [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], which can contribute to the recognition of unknown factors with clinical phenotypes of diabetes, causative pathways, patterns, and their interactions [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Many primary and secondary studies on the application of ML show that it is mainly used for the risk factors classification of glycemic control, the prediction and diagnosis of genetic and environmental factors, health care, and diabetes disease management [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Bibliometrics is described as mathematical techniques utilized to evaluate the quality and quantity of the existing scientific literature. They are used to investigate trends of research, citation analysis, authorship, journal impact, and analysis along with international collaboration in many scientific fields [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. According to the existing knowledge, no bibliometric research has been published in the scientific literature to date in the field of ML in diabetes. Given the high prevalence of this disease and the increasing trend of utilizing these models, numerous studies are inclined to employ AI models. Therefore, Analysis and mapping of ML in the context of diabetes using bibliometric indicators can give us a deep understanding of the present literature in this field and reveal future directions. Thus, this study aims to analysis and mapping of ML in the context of diabetes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="hsr271167-sec-0060"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0070"><label>2.1</label><title>Data Source</title><p>A bibliometric study was conducted via the Web of Science Core Collection database (WoSCC). WoS is a large multidisciplinary citation database involving complete citation hyperlinks and improved metadata supporting different information requirements [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0080"><label>2.2</label><title>Search Strategy</title><p>To build our data set, we searched from WoS in June 2024. Related keywords were used to set the search strategy. These keywords were selected based on primary studies, relevant systematic reviews, and Medical Subject Headings (MeSH). In addition, the key terms were reviewed and finalized by a panel of subject experts who were experienced in ML and diabetes studies. The search strategy was TS&#x02009;=&#x02009;(&#x0201c;Machine Learning&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Artificial Intelligence&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Deep Learning&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Support Vector Machine*&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Decision Tree*&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Neural Network*&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Random Forest*&#x0201d;) AND TS&#x02009;=&#x02009;(Diabete* OR &#x0201c;Diabetes Mellitus&#x0201d; OR Noninsulin&#x02010;Dependent OR &#x0201c;Noninsulin Dependent&#x0201d; OR Non&#x02010;Insulin&#x02010;Dependent OR &#x0201c;Noninsulin Dependent&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Insulin Dependent&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Type 2 Diabetes&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Type 1 Diabetes&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Pregnancy&#x02010;Induced Diabetes&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Gestational Diabetes&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Gestational Diabetes Mellitus&#x0201d;). We did not restrict the search by language. We limited our search to original articles, reviews, and proceedings, and excluded news, letters to editorials, abstracts of meetings, editorial materials, retraction, and retracted studies. We restricted our search to 2010&#x02010;01&#x02010;01 till 2023&#x02010;12&#x02010;31. Since ML models are new and because the new AI revolution started after 2010, the period from 2010 to 2023 has been considered in this paper.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0090"><label>2.3</label><title>Data Collection</title><p>After formulating the research question, articles were retrieved from the WoS database and saved as full records in tab&#x02010;delimited and CSV formats for further analysis. When we save a record from WoS as a full record, items such as authors, author full names, title of the paper, title of the source, author keywords, addresses, funding, and abstract are stored. These fields enable deep data analysis using scientific metrics. All search and data set creation steps were done on the same day.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0100"><label>2.4</label><title>Bibliometric Indicators Used</title><p>The bibliometric indices assessed included description, citation analysis, and trends of results, most prolific country, international research collaboration, most prolific authors, author collaboration, most cited papers, and research areas.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0110"><label>2.5</label><title>Data Analysis and Visualization Tools, and Data Extraction</title><p>The online services of WoS were used to retrieve reports of description and citation analysis of results. Microsoft Excel 2013 was employed for drawing trends of results. We calculated the number of times countries and authors were mentioned in the data set to detect the most prolific of them. The VOSviewer software (Version 1.6.20, Leiden University, Leiden, The Netherlands) was applied as a network analysis tool to show international research collaboration, author collaboration, and research domains. Keywords and authors with similar meanings but different spellings or expressions were merged. We created and utilized keywords and authors' thesauruses to ensure consistency and obtain accurate outputs from the VOSviewer. The papers included were sorted in descending order based on the citation frequency; we used the &#x0201c;sort by citations: highest first&#x0201d; option to arrange the highest to lowest cited papers. We selected the first ten most cited papers.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0120"><label>2.6</label><title>The Key Metrics Explanation</title><p>In the coauthorship network map, the nodes represent elements like countries, institutions, and authors. The node size is a reflection of the number of studies published by different countries, institutions, or authors. A link is a connection or a relation between two nodes. The links between nodes represent collaboration relationships, and the distance of the links between nodes signifies the strength of the cooperative relationships. Each link has a strength, represented by a positive numerical value. The higher this value, the stronger the link. the Links and Total link strength attributes indicate, respectively, the number of links of an item with other items and the total strength of the links of an item with other items. The node color denotes the clusters of countries in the same group. A cluster is a set of items included in a map. The color of the lines represents the time of the first cooperation between the two countries, institutions, or authors. The thickness of the lines is positively correlated to collaboration between the countries, institutions, or authors. In the co&#x02010;occurrence network map, the nodes signify different categories and keywords. The node size in co&#x02010;occurring research categories network denotes the number of studies in each category, and the node size in co&#x02010;occurring keywords network represents the frequency of occurrence. The links are representative of co&#x02010;occurrence relationships. The color of lines represents the time of the first co&#x02010;occurring between the two categories or keywords. The thickness of the lines is positively related to the number of studies with the same label between the categories, or positively correlated to the frequency of keywords occurring together [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="hsr271167-sec-0130"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0140"><label>3.1</label><title>Trends of Publication</title><p>A total of 5,222 results were adopted from the WoS on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023). There were 4,757 articles, followed by 465 reviews, and 39 proceeding papers. A total of 120 countries participated in writing articles. The retrieved articles had 92,182 citations, and the mean number of citations per item was 17. 65. There were 62,332 citing articles. A total of 27,155 authors contributed to the research. The language distribution was as follows: English (5,177), German (12), Chinese (6), Russian (5), and Korean (3). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the trend of published articles on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="hsr271167-fig-0001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Trend of published articles on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="HSR2-8-e71167-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0150"><label>3.2</label><title>Most Prolific Countries</title><p>In a total of 120 countries, the USA followed by China and India played the most important role in the research on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023). Regarding geographical distribution, four countries from Asia, three from Europe, two from the Americas, and one from Oceania were the most active. These countries include almost 92.7% of all papers (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="hsr271167-tbl-0001" content-type="Table"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Top ten most prolific countries in articles on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rank</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Country/Frequency</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%) (5,222)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Country/Total citations</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1270</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34310</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1079</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.66</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16271</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">775</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.84</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14362</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">England</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">417</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.98</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">England</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10675</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korea</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5230</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saudia Arabia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5055</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4474</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korea</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4141</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3788</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saudia Arabia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3535</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0160"><label>3.3</label><title>Country Collaboration Network</title><p>Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref> displays a visualization map of international research collaboration of countries that have published at least 10 articles on ML in the context of (2010&#x02013;2023). Accordingly, 67 countries are located in five clusters. The largest cluster (red) included 19 countries centered in Italy. Seventeen countries from Europe, one from Africa, and one from Ocean were shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, which established scientific communication with each other. The next cluster (green) had eighteen countries centered on India. Fourteen countries from Asia, with Egypt and Ethiopia from Africa and Russia from Europe, had scientific relations with each other. The third cluster, with ten countries centered on the USA along with China, Australia, and South Korea, is marked with blue color. Countries on the map's periphery, such as Jordan, Luxemburg, and North Irland, had less international cooperation than those in the center of the map.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="hsr271167-fig-0002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Illustration of international research collaboration with at least 10 articles on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023). For each of the 67 countries that met the thresholds, the total link strength of the coauthorship links with other countries was estimated. Those with the highest total link strength were finally selected.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="HSR2-8-e71167-g004" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0170"><label>3.4</label><title>Most Prolific Authors</title><p>The most prolific author on ML in the context of diabetes was Tien Yin Wong, with twenty&#x02010;two articles affiliated at Tsinghua University; after that, Pantelis Georgiou with twenty articles affiliated at the Imperial College London, and Pau Herrero, with nineteen articles affiliated at Tijuana Institute of Technology (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="hsr271167-tbl-0002" content-type="Table"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Most prolific authors in articles on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rank</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Authors</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country affiliation</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tien Yin Wong</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pantelis Georgiou</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">England</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pau Herrero</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">England</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giovanni Sparacino</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rajiv Raman</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andrea Facchinetti</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sobha Sivaprasad</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">England</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ramachandran Rajalakshmi</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viswanathan Mohan</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daniel Shu Wei Ting</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Singapore</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0180"><label>3.5</label><title>Author Collaboration Network</title><p>Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows the clustering of authors with at least 10 published scientific articles on studies regarding ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="hsr271167-fig-0003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Illustration of research networks of authors with at least 10 articles on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023). Authors in the same cluster had similar research interests. For each 27,155 authors, the total strength of coauthorship links with other authors was estimated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="HSR2-8-e71167-g003" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0190"><label>3.6</label><title>Most Cited Papers</title><p>Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref> includes the ten most cited articles on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="hsr271167-tbl-0003" content-type="Table"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Top ten most cited articles on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rank</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Title</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citations</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development and validation of a deep learning algorithm for detection of diabetic retinopathy in retinal fundus photographs</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JAMA&#x02010;Journal of the American Medical Association</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varun Gulshan</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3708</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Personalized nutrition by prediction of glycemic responses</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CELL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">David Zeevi</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1499</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development and validation of a deep learning system for diabetic retinopathy and related eye diseases using retinal images from multiethnic populations with diabetes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JAMA&#x02010;Journal of the American Medical Association</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daniel Shu Wei Ting</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1193</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deep Patient: An unsupervised representation to predict the future of patients from the electronic health records</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific Reports</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riccardo Miotto</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">778</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pivotal trial of an autonomous AI&#x02010;based diagnostic system for detection of diabetic retinopathy in primary care offices</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPJ Digital Medicine</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Michael D. Abramoff</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">651</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural products for drug discovery in the 21st century: Innovations for novel drug discovery</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">InternationaL Journal of Molecular Sciences</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nicholas Ekow Thomford</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">637</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improved automated detection of diabetic retinopathy on a publicly available data set through integration of deep learning</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigative Ophthalmology &#x00026; Visual Science</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Michael D. Abramoff.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">604</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A review of supervised object&#x02010;based land&#x02010;cover image classification</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISPRS Journal of Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lei Ma</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">575</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molecular de&#x02010;novo design through deep reinforcement learning</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal of Cheminformatics</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marcus Olivecrona</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">566</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Machine learning and data mining methods in diabetes research</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Computational and Structural Biotechnology Journal</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ioannis Kavakiotis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">549</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0200"><label>3.7</label><title>Research Areas</title><p>Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the author keywords of the retrieved literature on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023). A total of 10,239 keywords were identified in 5,222 articles. The keywords that appeared at least 10 times in the collected literature are categorized into eight clusters. The largest cluster is marked in red, in which the keywords machine learning, risk factors, Covid&#x02010;19, prediction model, type 2 diabetes, and gestational diabetes mellitus had the highest correlation with each other. The second cluster is marked in green, classification, support vector machine, system, and artificial neural network keywords had the highest correlation in this cluster. The third cluster is highlighted in blue in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="hsr271167-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. In this cluster, diabetic retinopathy, deep learning, artificial intelligence, glucose, automated detection, and optical coherence tomography had the highest correlation with each other. The furth cluster is displayed in yellow. In this cluster, deep learning, diabetes, diagnosis, and validation, had the highest correlation.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="Figure" id="hsr271167-fig-0004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Network visualization map of most frequent terms in author keywords with at least 10 documents of a keyword in the retrieved literature on ML in the context of diabetes (2010&#x02013;2023). For each of the 287 keywords, the overall strength of the co&#x02010;occurrence links with other keywords was estimated. The keywords with the highest total link strength were chosen.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="HSR2-8-e71167-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-7"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="hsr271167-sec-0210"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>This bibliometric study aimed to identify studies concerning ML in the context of diabetes. This study is among the first to conduct a bibliometric analysis on ML applications in diabetes care, including 5,222 articles adopted from WoS. The findings of this bibliometric analysis show a rich overview of the growth of scientific literature on ML in the context of diabetes over the past fourteen years, especially in 2018. This can be due to the high prevalence of diabetes worldwide and the application of ML to diagnose and treat diabetes in recent years. It can be predicted that the publication of papers will continue to flourish in the forthcoming years. Other bibliometric studies also confirm this finding [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>In this study, also the most prolific countries were identified. According to the results, USA has been at the forefront of ML research themes and diabetes, and the previous studies confirm the findings of this paper [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Several reasons can be presented for this finding. The presence of technology giants such as Google and Microsoft in this country can be a basis for the tendency or desire to publish more in this field. On the other hand, the migration of elites to the USA and their interest in studying in this country can be another justification for this result, leading to more scientific publications [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The bibliometric study recently published identified China as one of the leading country in conducting studies in this area [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. There are several reasons for this. One of the reasons is that almost half of the population of the world lives in China, it can be stated that the prevalence of diabetes and its complications, such as diabetic retinopathy, is higher in this country. On the other hand, China is among the semi&#x02010;developed ones, which have sufficient technical infrastructure to conduct ML studies, so it can be a motive for the researchers of these countries to use these models.</p><p>The present findings showed that in international collaborations, the USA has a high rate of internationally co&#x02010;authored papers on this topic. This finding is in line with many bibliometric studies [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The possible reason might be that academic papers on international collaboration enjoy a greater scientific impact than their national counterparts [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This can increase the motivation of researchers in their inclination for international cooperation. Other factors can be internationalized universities and strong English language skills in the USA that facilitate the formation of scientific cooperation networks. Emerging economies, such as India and Saudi Arabia, are leveraging international collaborations to harness ML capabilities in addressing the challenges of diabetes [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Collaborations between developed and developing nations, leveraging local expertise alongside advanced research methods, offer a model for other developing countries' research endeavors.</p><p>Another significant finding of this study is that the USA and China, in addition to having the largest share in scientific research on ML in the context of diabetes, also had the highest level of cooperation. Two bibliometric studies published recently also confirm this result [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The analysis of the countries in each scientific cooperation cluster showed that the geographical region does not have a key role in the degree of scientific cooperation. For example, although China and India were the most active countries in this field in terms of scientific production in the second and third ranks and shared a common geographical border, they did not have significant cooperation with each other. This problem can reject the effect of geographical regions on scientific participation in this field. The results show that approximately one&#x02010;third of the world's countries collaborate to produce research on ML in the context of diabetes. With more complex and challenging issues humans face in diabetes, international collaboration has become integral to ML [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Therefore, it can be a chance to resolve complex problems in this area. Evidence has shown that international collaboration is at the core of the ML Community to serve humans in more complex conditions. For instance, with the global emergence of the COVID&#x02010;19 pandemic, artificial intelligence scientists have worked with field experts, including epidemiologists, virologists, and clinicians [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Cooperation with other countries was highest in English&#x02010;speaking countries including the USA, England, and Australia. In line with this, Fu et al. showed that researchers all over the world tend to collaborate with English&#x02010;speaking countries to find sponsors who allocate funds for this type of research, decision&#x02010;making, and so forth [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>This paper also analyzes the collaboration among authors. Author collaboration analysis has allowed us to identify authors who collaborated in the clusters with color distinction. These clusters also provided the possibility to identify collaborative groups. The results show that Tien Yin Wong, Sobha Sivaprasad, and Ramachandran Rajalakshmi had the highest scientific cooperation with each other and with other researchers. These three researchers are leaders in this field, and following their works can determine the direction of future research in ML and diabetes, which will be useful as a guide, especially for early career researchers.</p><p>In scientometrics studies, co&#x02010;occurrence analysis of keywords is common to identify the research topic in a specific field and over a specific period. The correlation between the words &#x0201c;machine learning, prediction model, risk factors, type 2 diabetes, association, and prevalence&#x0201d; shows that to create or adapt a prediction model in the field of diabetes, researchers need to identify the risk factors of this disease. They also should pay attention to the prevalence of the outcome in this data set. Correlation between words in another category (diabetic retinopathy, deep learning, artificial intelligence, convolutional neural network (CNN), automated detection, validation, optical coherence tomography (OCT)) also shows that if there is a data set that includes OCT images of patients with diabetic retinopathy, DL models can be created using CNN to help physicians and diabetes specialists make decisions in screening or diagnosing this disease, and the previous study confirm the findings of this paper [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The analysis shows a strong correlation between several keywords. This suggests that researchers need to consider not only risk factors and prevalence but also the type of risk factors when creating or adapting prediction models. This implies that the prevalence of the outcome variable within the data set is a crucial factor in the research methodology.</p><p>To our knowledge, this study is among the first to conduct a bibliometric analysis on ML applications in diabetes care, Nevertheless, the current study has some limitations. Specifically, the analyzed articles were only retrieved from WoS. However, future researchers could consider alternative sources of data collection, such as Scopus or Google Scholar. The results of this paper can help early career who intend to enter the field of ML and diabetes create a practical and comprehensive ML model. Exclusion of other major databases such as Scopus or Google Scholar could influence the findings. Highly cited articles from earlier years may have a disproportionate impact on the analysis. Publications in English dominate the data set. Also, the most cited papers in this field show that the most important feature of these papers is the high generalizability of their ML models and the evaluation of their models by subject experts in the field of diabetes. Therefore, the researchers of this paper recommend that for future studies, in addition to the external and internal evaluation of these models, assessment by the subject experts in diabetes should also be considered as a complementary method in conducting studies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="hsr271167-sec-0220"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>ML has started to change some important aspects of health care, such as diagnosis and screening of diseases. A bibliometric study was done to analyze the global condition and trends of research in the field of ML and diabetes, which allows readers to achieve a sound understanding of the literature on this field. The study highlights the importance of considering risk factors and prevalence in developing ML prediction models, and emphasizes the need for expert validation of these models. Funding should target international collaborations using ML to improve diabetes care in lower&#x02010;income nations. The findings offer guidance for early&#x02010;career researchers in this field.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0230"><label>6</label><title>Policy Recommendations</title><p>This study can guide policymakers in developing systems to help physicians in decision&#x02010;making. In addition, the findings will be useful for governments to guide future budgets for target studies.</p><p>Optimizing the allocation of research funding by identifying high&#x02010;impact areas and researchers, and Guiding investments in research infrastructure based on identified needs and capacity gaps.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0240"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>
<bold>Arezoo Ghamgosar:</bold> conceptualization, methodology, formal analysis, validation, investigation, writing &#x02013; original draft, writing &#x02013; review and editing, visualization, data curation. <bold>Leila Nemati&#x02010;Anaraki:</bold> validation, investigation, supervision, data curation. <bold>Maryam Zarghani:</bold> software, data curation, investigation. <bold>Hooman Bazri:</bold> methodology, software, data curation, formal analysis, writing &#x02013; review and editing. <bold>Leila Ahmadian:</bold> data curation. <bold>Zahra Galavi:</bold> data curation. <bold>Somaye Norouzi:</bold> investigation, data curation, software.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0250"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The authors have nothing to report.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0260"><title>Consent</title><p>The authors have nothing to report.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="hsr271167-sec-0270"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec id="hsr271167-sec-0300"><label>1</label><title>Transparency Statement</title><p>The lead author Somaye Norouzi affirms that this manuscript is an honest, accurate, and transparent account of the study being reported; that no important aspects of the study have been omitted; and that any discrepancies from the study as planned (and, if relevant, registered) have been explained.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="hsr271167-sec-0290"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. The datasets utilized and/or analyzed within the present research are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="hsr271167-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Haneef</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Kab</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Hrzic</surname>
</string-name>, et al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Use of Artificial Intelligence for Public Health Surveillance: A Case Study to Develop a Machine Learning&#x02010;Algorithm to Estimate the Incidence of Diabetes Mellitus in France</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Archives of Public Health</source>
<volume>79</volume> (<year>2021</year>): <elocation-id>168</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34551816</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="hsr271167-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Lantz</surname>
</string-name>, <source>Machine Learning With R: Expert Techniques for Predictive Modeling</source> (<publisher-name>Packt publishing ltd</publisher-name>, <year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Obermeyer</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name>
<given-names>E. J.</given-names>
<surname>Emanuel</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Predicting the Future&#x02014;Big Data, Machine Learning, and Clinical Medicine</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>
<volume>375</volume>, no. <issue>13</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>1216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27682033</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
<surname>Antoniadi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Du</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Guendouz</surname>
</string-name>, et al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Current Challenges and Future Opportunities for XAI in Machine Learning&#x02010;Based Clinical Decision Support Systems: A Systematic Review</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Applied Sciences</source>
<volume>11</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <elocation-id>5088</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Yun</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Oh</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T. H.</given-names>
<surname>Hong</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Kim</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Prediction of Mortality in Surgical Intensive Care Unit Patients Using Machine Learning Algorithms</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Frontiers in Medicine</source>
<volume>8</volume> (<year>2021</year>): <elocation-id>621861</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33869245</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<given-names>H. M.</given-names>
<surname>Krumholz</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Big Data and New Knowledge in Medicine: The Thinking, Training, and Tools Needed for a Learning Health System</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Health Affairs</source>
<volume>33</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>1163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25006142</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Kavakiotis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Tsave</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Salifoglou</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Maglaveras</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Vlahavas</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Chouvarda</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Machine Learning and Data Mining Methods in Diabetes Research</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Computational and Structural Biotechnology Journal</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28138367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<given-names>G. S.</given-names>
<surname>Collins</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Mallett</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Omar</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L.&#x02010;M.</given-names>
<surname>Yu</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Developing Risk Prediction Models for Type 2 Diabetes: A Systematic Review of Methodology and Reporting</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>BMC Medicine</source>
<volume>9</volume> (<year>2011</year>): <elocation-id>103</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21902820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Lamain&#x02013;de Ruiter</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Kwee</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. A.</given-names>
<surname>Naaktgeboren</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Franx</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. G. M.</given-names>
<surname>Moons</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. P. H.</given-names>
<surname>Koster</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Prediction Models for the Risk of Gestational Diabetes: A Systematic Review</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Diagnostic and Prognostic Research</source>
<volume>1</volume> (<year>2017</year>): <elocation-id>3</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31093535</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Dinh</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Miertschin</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Young</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. D.</given-names>
<surname>Mohanty</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>A Data&#x02010;Driven Approach to Predicting Diabetes and Cardiovascular Disease With Machine Learning</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making</source>
<volume>19</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <elocation-id>211</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31694707</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Norouzi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Kamel Ghalibaf</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Sistani</surname>
</string-name>, et al., &#x0201c;<article-title>A Mobile Application for Managing Diabetic Patients' Nutrition: A Food Recommender System</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Archives of Iranian Medicine</source>
<volume>21</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>466</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>472</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30415555</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="hsr271167-cit-0012">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y.&#x02010;L.</given-names>
<surname>Cheng</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y.&#x02010;R.</given-names>
<surname>Wu</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>K.&#x02010;D.</given-names>
<surname>Lin</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>C.&#x02010;H. R.</given-names>
<surname>Lin</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, and <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<given-names>I.&#x02010;M.</given-names>
<surname>Lin</surname>
</string-name>
</person-group>, ed., <part-title>Using Machine Learning for the Risk Factors Classification of Glycemic Control in Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</part-title>.&#x0201d; in <source>Healthcare</source>. <publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name>, <year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Dharmarathne</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T. N.</given-names>
<surname>Jayasinghe</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Bogahawaththa</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. P. P.</given-names>
<surname>Meddage</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
<surname>Rathnayake</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>A Novel Machine Learning Approach for Diagnosing Diabetes With a Self&#x02010;Explainable Interface</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Healthcare Analytics</source>
<volume>5</volume> (<year>2024</year>): <elocation-id>100301</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<given-names>W. M.</given-names>
<surname>Sweileh</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Analysis and Mapping of Global Research Publications on Point&#x02010;of&#x02010;Care Testing for Infectious Diseases</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>953</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38764304</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<given-names>T. N.</given-names>
<surname>Poly</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. M.</given-names>
<surname>Islam</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. A.</given-names>
<surname>Walther</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. C.</given-names>
<surname>Lin</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>Y. C.</given-names>
<surname>(Jack) Li</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Artificial Intelligence in Diabetic Retinopathy: Bibliometric Analysis</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine</source>
<volume>231</volume> (<year>2023</year>): <elocation-id>107358</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36731310</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Lu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Yang</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Systematic Bibliometric and Visualized Analysis of Research Hotspots and Trends on the Application of Artificial Intelligence in Ophthalmic Disease Diagnosis</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Frontiers in Pharmacology</source>
<volume>13</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>930520</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35754490</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<given-names>W. M.</given-names>
<surname>Sweileh</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Analysis and Mapping of Harm Reduction Research in the Context of Injectable Drug Use: Identifying Research Hotspots, Gaps and Future Directions</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Harm Reduction Journal</source>
<volume>21</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2024</year>): <elocation-id>131</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38987762</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Wu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Duan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Tian</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Deng</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Research Trends in the Application of Artificial Intelligence in Oncology: A Bibliometric and Network Visualization Study</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Frontiers in Bioscience&#x02010;Landmark</source>
<volume>27</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>254</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Shen</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Wu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Chen</surname>
</string-name>, et al., &#x0201c;<article-title>The Global Research of Artificial Intelligence on Prostate Cancer: A 22&#x02010;year Bibliometric Analysis</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Frontiers in Oncology</source>
<volume>12</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>843735</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35299747</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Agarwal</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Ganguli</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Gaul&#x000e9;</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Smith</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Why US Immigration Matters for the Global Advancement of Science</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Research Policy</source>
<volume>52</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2023</year>): <elocation-id>104659</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Shao</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Jin</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Lou</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Ye</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Overview of Global Publications on Machine Learning in Diabetic Retinopathy From 2011 to 2021: Bibliometric Analysis</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Frontiers in Endocrinology</source>
<volume>13</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>1032144</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36589855</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Higaki</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Uetani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Ikeda</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Co&#x02010;Authorship Network Analysis in Cardiovascular Research Utilizing Machine Learning (2009&#x02013;2019)</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Medical Informatics</source>
<volume>143</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <elocation-id>104274</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32987350</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Kim</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Lee</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Park</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Machine Learning for Mental Health in Social Media: Bibliometric Study</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Medical Internet Research</source>
<volume>23</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <elocation-id>e24870</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33683209</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Kohus</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Demeter</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G. P.</given-names>
<surname>Szigeti</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Kun</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Luk&#x000e1;cs</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Czak&#x000f3;</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>The Influence of International Collaboration on the Scientific Impact in V4 Countries</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Publications</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>35</elocation-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Maziak</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Critchley</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Zaman</surname>
</string-name>, et al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Mediterranean Studies of Cardiovascular Disease and Hyperglycemia: Analytical Modeling of Population Socio&#x02010;Economic Transitions (Medchamps)&#x02014;Rationale and Methods</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Public Health</source>
<volume>58</volume> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>553</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23111372</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Luengo&#x02010;Oroz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Hoffmann Pham</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Bullock</surname>
</string-name>, et al., &#x0201c;<article-title>Artificial Intelligence Cooperation to Support the Global Response to COVID&#x02010;19</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Nature Machine Intelligence</source>
<volume>2</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
<surname>Tang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Ma</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Internationalizing AI: Evolution and Impact of Distance Factors</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Scientometrics</source>
<volume>127</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35034995</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<given-names>Y. C.</given-names>
<surname>Fu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Marques</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>Y.&#x02010;H.</given-names>
<surname>Tseng</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. J. W.</given-names>
<surname>Powell</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>D. P.</given-names>
<surname>Baker</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>An Evolving International Research Collaboration Network: Spatial and Thematic Developments in Co&#x02010;Authored Higher Education Research, 1998&#x02013;2018</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Scientometrics</source>
<volume>127</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>1403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1429</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hsr271167-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="hsr271167-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<given-names>E. H.</given-names>
<surname>Sep&#x000fa;lveda&#x02010;Oviedo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Trav&#x000e9;&#x02010;Massuy&#x000e8;s</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Subias</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Pavlov</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Alonso</surname>
</string-name>, &#x0201c;<article-title>Fault Diagnosis of Photovoltaic Systems Using Artificial Intelligence: A Bibliometric Approach</article-title>,&#x0201d; <source>Heliyon</source>
<volume>9</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2023</year>): <elocation-id>e21491</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37954345</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>