<p xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par22">This study has a number of limitations. First, our study attempted to run and compare reasonably diverse methods for predicting AD risk, with the advantage of implementing them in a unified dataset. As a result, we found that the PRS and ML prediction showed a similar prediction performance based upon ranking individuals according by their prediction scores. The predictions from ML and PRS, however, were highly correlated, explaining the similarity of the prediction accuracies and reducing the likelihood that an ensemble of the different methods would improve prediction. Second, the methods used for selection of top SNPs in interpreting model results reflect inherent differences in how the ML approaches work, and no standard thresholds exist at the moment for identifying important features across these distinct frameworks. This methodological variability, which is a broader challenge in the field, likely contributes to the incomplete overlap between the top SNPs identified by different ML approaches, making replication in external summary statistics a critical step to ensure robust findings. Third, the influence of <italic>APOE</italic> status on model outcomes is a key component of all models in the study. While <italic>APOE</italic> SNPs were included as predictors, we did not conduct analyses stratified by <italic>APOE</italic> carrier status, especially &#949;3/&#949;3, &#949;3/&#949;4, or &#949;4/&#949;4 carriers. Future work should explore whether predictive accuracy and associations differ meaningfully across these strata. Finally, although our post-hoc analyses indicate that cohort or genotyping centre effects do not drive associations or predictions, alternative machine learning approaches such as federated learning (FL) may improve modelling where underlying predictor distributions diverge<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>, while also allowing for models which include data from more cohorts without diminishing privacy. Indeed, within a central learning paradigm, current best practices for data harmonisation involve merging datasets based on shared high-quality SNPs that have undergone rigorous quality control, ensuring high imputation accuracy, reasonably large minor allele frequencies (MAF), and other metrics in each separate study. However, these QC steps alone do not guarantee that differences arising from ancestry, clinical assessment criteria, and genotyping chips or batches used to generate the data are fully accounted for. Applying flexible ML within an FL framework leverages the advantages of client-specific data, which is often more homogeneous as it is typically generated locally, within the same population, using similar clinical assessments and the same genotyping chip. Results from each &#8220;client&#8221; can then inform analyses for other clients by tuning parameters (e.g., increasing or decreasing neural network weights for variants in specific genomic regions), creating a more flexible and adaptive analysis framework.</p>