<p xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par14">ML methods correctly identified the lead SNPs used to calculate the <italic>APOE</italic> haplotype, rs7412 and rs429358, as having the greatest impact on the model, in contrast to classical univariable linear models (traditional GWAS) which do not distinguish between top variants by <italic>p</italic>-value, and rank rs7412 lower (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). PRS for AD risk prediction perform best when modelled with two predictors: PRS calculated without the <italic>APOE</italic> region and a separately coded weighting of the <italic>APOE</italic> e2 and e4 alleles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Here, we demonstrate that ML approaches can accurately identify <italic>APOE</italic> clusters and achieve comparable prediction accuracy without including the derived <italic>APOE</italic> variable as a second predictor. ML approaches further detected the lead SNPs identified in large meta-analyses GWAS for several key genes, including <italic>BIN1</italic> (rs6733839), <italic>PICALM</italic> (rs3851179), <italic>ABCA7</italic> (rs3752246, a coding variant), <italic>CASS4</italic> (rs6069736) and <italic>CR1</italic> (rs4844610). More broadly, ML highlighted SNPs in around 22% of genes identified by larger meta-analysis GWAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, while comparison to a GWAS undertaken on the same (EADB-core) split that was used to train machine learning models, showed that 100% of genome-wide significant SNPs (<italic>p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;5 &#215; 10<sup>&#8722;8</sup>) were retrieved by ML approaches. This demonstrates that the majority of findings expected under a linear additive GWAS paradigm can be prioritised using flexible machine learning models. Though strides have been made in ML-based prediction of AD from genetic data, for example<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, to our knowledge we present the first well-powered, genome-wide ML-based gene discovery study detecting nearly a quarter of known genes found in larger GWAS meta-analyses from the literature which contain around twenty times the sample size, while also identifying multiple putative regions with credible associations to AD biology, marking an important benchmark for these methods.</p>