<p xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par20">Comparing individual scores, ML predictions achieved correlations of 0.8-0.84 with PRS, indicating ML models give predictions which are broadly consistent with well-established approaches. It also shows that identification of novel signals through flexible modelling of complex effects will introduce deviations from the predictions of a simple linear additive model. Disease risk prediction from ML, as assessed by AUC, was higher (but not significantly) than PRS. Similar results have been reported in psychiatry<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> and coronary artery disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. This is likely to be due to several reasons. First, SNPs in general are (at best) only correlated with the causal variants, making it particularly difficult to detect nonlinear effects and interactions, which are the main potential advantages of ML over PRS. Second, genetic predictors are weak as compared to some other predictors (e.g. biomarkers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>), and the upper bound for AUC in complex trait genetics in practice falls substantially below 1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Weak predictor-response relationships are an inherent challenge to finding patterns with flexible models, and complex models may at-present still be under-powered to achieve a clear improvement in AUC. Third, large GWAS discover and replicate SNPs, which in the resulting summary statistics show small association effect sizes. The effect sizes may however be higher in more homogenous samples. For example, the OR for <italic>APOE</italic> is around 3.4 in samples of mean age 72&#8722;73 years<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup> but is reduced in samples over 90 years<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. In pathologically-confirmed samples, which are also generally older than clinical samples, some of the GWAS-derived SNP effect sizes are higher than reported in clinically-assessed AD GWAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. In more homogenous samples in terms of age, population, and cognitive scores (such as The <italic>Alzheimer&#8217;s Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI)</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>), the AD PRS AUC are higher than that in clinical samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Thus, summary statistics from large GWAS meta-analyses enable PRS which predict with moderate AUC in any data set, but which do not achieve high accuracy as effect sizes are averaged across many studies with slightly different features such as recruitment criteria and outcome definitions, and therefore genetic architectures, rather than being specific to a particular one.</p>