<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Another significant finding of this study is that the USA and China, in addition to having the largest share in scientific research on ML in the context of diabetes, also had the highest level of cooperation. Two bibliometric studies published recently also confirm this result [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The analysis of the countries in each scientific cooperation cluster showed that the geographical region does not have a key role in the degree of scientific cooperation. For example, although China and India were the most active countries in this field in terms of scientific production in the second and third ranks and shared a common geographical border, they did not have significant cooperation with each other. This problem can reject the effect of geographical regions on scientific participation in this field. The results show that approximately one&#8208;third of the world's countries collaborate to produce research on ML in the context of diabetes. With more complex and challenging issues humans face in diabetes, international collaboration has become integral to ML [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Therefore, it can be a chance to resolve complex problems in this area. Evidence has shown that international collaboration is at the core of the ML Community to serve humans in more complex conditions. For instance, with the global emergence of the COVID&#8208;19 pandemic, artificial intelligence scientists have worked with field experts, including epidemiologists, virologists, and clinicians [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Cooperation with other countries was highest in English&#8208;speaking countries including the USA, England, and Australia. In line with this, Fu et al. showed that researchers all over the world tend to collaborate with English&#8208;speaking countries to find sponsors who allocate funds for this type of research, decision&#8208;making, and so forth [<xref rid="hsr271167-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p>